Guide to the Sanford Richardson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Sanford Richardson Papers
1857-1879
RG 311
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(4 boxes)
Extensive correspondence, reports, and an autobiography document the work of Sanford Richardson, missionary among the Armenians in Ottoman Turkey from 1857 to 1879, serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions.
Richardson, Sanford, 1825-1886
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series:
I. Letterbooks
II. Biographical Documentation
III. Mission Records
Biographical / Historical
Sanford Richardson was born in Monroe, Ohio in 1825 his to Alpheus and Lucy Cove Richardson. In 1836 the family emigrated to Illinois. While attending Knox College in Galesburg, Illinois Richardson was baptized by Presbyterian evangelist Rev. George W. Gale. After graduation from Knox College in 1846, Richardson spent five years in teaching and in Bible and tract distribution before entering Union Theological Seminary in New York in 1851. Following his graduation from seminary and ordination in 1854, Richardson was appointed as a missionary to the Armenians of Western Asia by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions.
Richardson married Rhoda Ann Scott (1828-1915) in 1848, with whom he had five children, four born in Turkey. In Ottoman Turkey, Richardson worked among the Armenians in Erzroom (1854-1856), Arabkir (1856-1866), and Broosa (1867-1879). He returned to the United States in 1879 and died in 1886 in Cazenovia, Illinois.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2018.
Scope and Contents
The Sanford Richardson papers include six letterbooks of correspondence related to his service as a missionary to the Armenians in Turkey from 1857 to 1879. The letterbooks contain both copies of the letters Richardson sent and the original letters that he received, arranged in general chronological order. An index at the back of each volume provides identification of letters from particular individuals or regarding places and topics. Correspondents included clergy and missionaries, family members, diplomats, consular agents, Turkish officials, Armenian and Greek clergy and educators, as well as American educators, journalists, and medical doctors. Letters are interspersed with other documents, including a few sketches and photographs.
Letters exchanged with clergy and fellow missionaries scattered throughout the Ottoman Empire provide descriptive details about their work in Bible and tract translation, distribution of religious literature, the establishment of schools, churches, and medical facilities, as well as the training of native Armenians as teachers and preachers. Frequently discussed were the religious and political problems they faced from leaders and clergymen of the Armenian Apostolic Church as well as "Papists" and Muslim officials and clergy. Other discussed topics include religious, political, and military incidents related to the Crimean War, the Russo-Turkish War and the American Civil War, local famines and epidemics, rural uprisings, and the procurement of materials. Letters from medical missionaries in Turkey such as David H. Nutting, Fayette Jewett, Moses Parmelee and H.S. West describe their medical and religious work among the indigenous populations.
Letters sent to Richardson's parents, siblings, and in-laws provide extensive detail regarding missionary social activities, travels, and the schooling of their children.
The letterbooks are supplemented by Richardson's 300 page manuscript autobiography, which he wrote after his return from Turkey. This unpublished work describes Richardson's relationships with fellow missionaries and mission officials, their mission activities, and trips taken through the countryside, often by caravan and endangered by bandits and Kurds.
The Mission Records of Series III include detailed minutes of annual meetings of the Armenian (later Western Turkey) Mission of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, as well as annual reports of the Arabkir, Broosa, and Marash mission stations.
Missions -- Turkey; Armenians--Missions; Richardson, Sanford, 1825-1886
- Letterbooks, Series I
  - Photocopies of indices from letterbook volumes 1 - 6, 1857-1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopies of the indices from the six volumes are gathered together to facilitate usability. Each handwritten index provides an alphabetical sequence of names and topics with notation of relevant pages in the volume. This folder also contains an alphabetical index of clergymen/missionaries mentioned in the volumes, which was prepared by the vendor of the collection, and the vendor's description of the collection.
  - Volume 1, 1857-1860 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Volume 1 contains 868 pages, including 349 letters, and has a detailed index at the end of the volume. Letters in this volume that were written by Sanford Richardson date from 1857 July 17 to 1859 December 31 and documents received by Richardson date from 1857 March 24 to 1860 March 20. The volume includes a few press-copy illustrations by Richardson related to the Arabkir mission.
    Prominent correspondents in Volume 1 include Rufus Anderson, Herbert Morton Barnum, Harrison Gray Otis Dwight, William Goodell, Cyrus Hamlin, Elias Riggs, Henry Van Lennep, and George Washburn.
  - Volume 2, 1860-1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Volume 2 contains 610 pages, including 271 letters, and has a detailed index at the end of the volume. Letters in this volume that were written by Sanford Richardson date from 1860 January 1 to 1861 February 22 and documents received by Richardson date from 1860 January 10 to 1860 December 18.
    Prominent correspondents in Volume 2 include Rufus Anderson, Herbert Morton Barnum, Isaac G. Bliss, Harrison Gray Otis Dwight, William Goodell, Cyrus Hamlin, D. W. Marsh, Elias Riggs, Henry Van Lennep, and George Washburn.
  - Volume 3, 1861-1862 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Volume 3 contains 927 pages, including 355 letters, and has a detailed index at the end of the volume. Letters in this volume that were written by Sanford Richardson date from 1861 January 1 to 1862 June 5 and documents received by Richardson date from 1861 January 1 to 1862 May 31.
    Prominent correspondents in Volume 3 include Rufus Anderson, Herbert Morton Barnum, Isaac G. Bliss, Harrison Gray Otis Dwight, A. B. Goodall, Cyrus Hamlin, David H. Nutting, and George A. Pollard.
  - Volume 4, 1862-1864 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Volume 4 contains 889 pages, including 425 letters, and has a detailed index at the end of the volume. Letters in this volume that were written by Sanford Richardson date from 1862 June 6 to 1864 April 7 and documents received by Richardson date from 1862 July 14 to 1864 February 25.
    Prominent correspondents in Volume 4 include Rufus Anderson, Herbert Morton Barnum, Isaac G. Bliss, David H. Nutting, Elias Riggs, William Gottlieb Schauffler, Henry Van Lennep, and George Washburn. The volume also includes an annual report and financial records for the Arabkir Mission.
  - Volume 5, 1864-1871 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Volume 5 contains 1532 pages, including 565 letters, and has a detailed index at the end of the volume. Letters in this volume that were written by Sanford Richardson date from 1864 April 20 to 1871 December 30 and documents received by Richardson date from 1864 March 22 to 1871 August 18.
    Prominent correspondents in Volume 5 include Rufus Anderson, Herbert Morton Barnum, Isaac G. Bliss, W. G. Clark, J. K. Greene, Elias Riggs, William Gottlieb Schauffler, and George Washburn. There is a letter from noted British explorer Henry M Stanley. The volume also includes annual reports of mission stations.
  - Volume 6, 1872-1879 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Volume contains 1836 pages, including 583 letters, and has a detailed index at the end of the volume. Letters in this volume that were written by Sanford Richardson date from 1872 March 2 to 1879 March 1 and documents received by Richardson date from 1872 February 29 to 1879 January 2.
    Prominent correspondents in Volume 6 include Isaac G. Bliss, H. O. Dwight, and G. W. Wood. The volume also includes reports related to the mission and three photographs.
- Biographical Documentation, Series II
  - Ms. autobiography: "Regions Beyond; or Sketches of Life and Labor in Armenia Major and Armenia Minor by Sanford Richardson, Missionary of the A.B.C.F.M" (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    The date 1854 is written in pencil on the title page but the work was written following Richardson's return to the United States in 1879. The manuscript is 303 pages.
  - Additional biographical information (Box 4, Folder 4)
    This folder contains printouts of biographical and genealogical information about the Richardson family and selected prominent correspondents, compiled by the vendor of the collection.
- Mission Records, Series III
  The minutes and reports in this series are handwritten copies.
  - Armenian / Western Turkey Mission
    - "Minutes of the 17th Annual Meeting of the Armenian Mission, held at Constantinople", 1857-05-1857-06 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Minutes of the 18th Annual Meeting of the Armenian Mission", 1858 May - June (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Sections of the meeting are reported as being held in different locales, including Pera and Bebek.
    - "Minutes of the 19th Annual Meeting of the Northern Armenian Mission", 1859 June (Box 4, Folder 7)
      The handwritten minutes record a series of meetings held in various locales, include Pera, Bebek, and "Yeni Kapoo."
    - "Minutes of the 20th Annual Meeting of the Armenian Mission, held at Kharpoot", 1860 May - June (Box 4, Folder 8)
      "With full notes, by Rev. W. W. Meriam, of the remarks on Division of Mission, Seminaries Male and Female at Kharpoot, occupation of Erzroom, Mr. Dunmore's and Mr. Bliss's Sermons,etc.."
    - "Minutes of the 28th Annual Meeting of the Mission to Western Turkey", 1868 May (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Sessions held in Bebek, Constantinople.
    - "Minutes of the 29th Annual Meeting of the Mission to Western Turkey", 1869 May (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Sessions held in Galata, Bebek, "Yeni Kapou"
    - "Minutes of the 30th Annual Meeting of the W. Turkey Mission", 1870 May (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Sesssions held in Galata, Bebek.
    - "Minutes of the Thirty-Second Annual Meeting of the W. T. Mission", 1872 May - June (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Sessions held at Bible House, Constantinople.
    - "Minutes of the Thirty-third Annual Meeting of the W. T. Mission", 1873 May (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "Minutes of the Thirty-Fourth Annual Meeting of the W. T. Mission", 1874 June (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Sessions held at Bible House, Constantinople"
    - "Minutes of the 35th Annual Meeting of the W. T. Mission", 1875 May (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Sessions held at Bible House, Constantinople
    - "Minutes of the 36 Annual Meeting of the W. T. Mission", 1877 April - May (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Minutes of the Thirty-Seventh Annual Meeting of the Mission to Western Turkey of the American Board", 1878 May - June (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Sessions held at Bible House, Constantinople. Includes list of Mission committees and copies of letters.
    - "Minutes of the Thirty-Eighth Annual Meeting of the MIssion to W. Turkey", 1879 May - June (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Arabkir Station
    - "4th Annual Report, Arabkir Station", 1857 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Broosa Station
    - "Report of the Broosa Station 1869-1870 by Dr. Schneider" (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "Report of the Broosa Station 1870-1871 by Dr. Schneider" (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Marash Station
    - Bound volume: "Records of Marash Station", 1857-1879 (Box 4, Folder 21)